All right. Let's go.
2012 Dalibor from the Czech Republic.
Good luck, Dalibor.
And we have another Sicilian. And we
have faced virtually no open Sicilians.
This is This is a plague on humanity.
Everybody's going knight c3 now. It's
crazy.
And we've already faced this move like
three or four times, but hey, this is a
realistic cross-section of what people
play nowadays. Opening fashions change.
I feel like even like two, three years
ago, open Sicilian was
you know, everybody was playing it and
the people who weren't were playing the
Alapin. Now, people are going for all
sorts of knight c3 variations. We're
going to respond with a move that
I talked about
uh previously. Rather than going knight
c6, and the downside of knight c6 is
that it allows this incredibly tricky
sideline bishop b5. We've already faced
this sideline. I've gotten into trouble
against it. And around that time, I
talked about the immediate g6, which is
very uncommon, but it sidesteps a lot of
annoying lines. If white is a Grand Prix
Attack player, then it doesn't really
matter what you play. You can play
knight c6 or g6. Our opponent is a Grand
Prix Attack player, which is knight c3
followed by f4. The Grand Prix Attack is
one of the most dangerous systems
against the Sicilian. I haven't
refreshed my own theory in a long time.
So, this is going to be really fun.
Let's see if we can avoid getting
checkmated. First things first, let's
fianchetto our bishop.
And usually white plays knight f3. And
in this position, we have several
different setups. Essentially, we can
start by playing d6, or we can start
with a more conventional knight to c6.
Let's play more conventionally with
knight c6.
And bishop c4 is the old school move.
The new school move is bishop to b5.
This is a more positional way of playing
the Grand Prix attack. Bishop C4 is the
sort of old-school method where you're
aiming directly at F7 and you can watch
my previous videos for more of a
background on the Grand Prix attack
because this is a high-level
higher-level game. Um I'm going to skip
straight to the sort of juice and talk
about the moves themselves. Afterward,
we'll do a little bit of little bit more
theoretical investigating. Okay, so
as far as I know, the most popular setup
and this was popularized many decades
ago is what was taught to me as the
Botvinnik setup and that is where you go
E6 and then you put the knight on E7.
It's essentially like fianchetto, knight
on E7, knight on C6 and you can do it
with white as well. This is a setup this
is a system, not necessarily a specific
setup against a particular opening. E6,
as far as I remember, there's this very
dangerous gambit line where white
responds with D4. So there's a lot of
theory associated with the move E6 and
because I haven't refreshed my knowledge
in a long time, I'm inclined to play a
slightly more modest move. Maybe we can
start with D6 and then we can either
play E6 or we can play a line that I
introduced a couple of speedrun games
ago where we bring our knight actually
out to H6. This is an also an
interesting line against the Grand Prix
attack.
Let me think about what we want to do
here. So E6
I don't really want to play but we can.
We can start with D6 and then play E6.
That's totally possible. Let's do that.
Let's start with D6.
And now that we have opened up our
bishop, one thing that we don't want to
do here is play Bishop G4. This is a
terrible move that walks right into this
very well-known tactic, Bishop takes F7
check followed by knight G5. So
definitely not Bishop G4.
We can play knight F6 but it was taught
to me very long time ago that you want
to avoid bringing your knight out to F6
in the Grand Prix attack and in the
closed Sicilian. I'll talk a little bit
more about that after the game. I think
e6 is a much safer option.
Uh and it's an option that makes it more
difficult for white to jump-start his uh
king side attack. So, let's let's go e6.
Knight h6 maybe is a move here, but with
the bishop already out on c4, there's
also by the way the move knight a5. I've
seen this move played sometimes knight
a5 in order to kick the bishop away from
this diagonal, so it should make logical
sense that you won't you would want to
do that because f7 is our weakest pawn.
But, let's go e6. Let's let's play more
conventionally in this game.
I'm definitely out theoried. Okay, d4.
This is uh this is getting a little
disturbing because d4 here I'm not too
familiar with. So, basically I'm on my
own and this is where I might get
crushed if I do. Okay, but we're going
to try to use general opening principles
to figure out our way out of this
opening. Okay. So, the idea of d4 is to
blast open the center and as far as I
remember after c takes d4, white
responds with knight to b5.
Uh this is a very dangerous line and we
could get in trouble here. After c d4,
white plays knight b5 and then white is
exerting pressure on d6, but the main
idea is that if we respond with a move
like a6, white takes the pawn on d4.
Okay, and once the d file is opened, the
d6 pawn
is quite a bit weaker. It's easier to
attack. Now, I don't think we have much
of a choice here. We have to take this
pawn. Maybe we could also take it with
the knight, but I don't really see a
reason to give up our well-developed
knight. I think we should start with c
takes d4 and now we should invest a
little bit of time. So,
one thing that I really don't want to do
is play a6 because what is white's next
move likely to be? Well, likely it's
going to be knight takes d4 anyway, so I
think a6 is I wouldn't say a waste of
time entirely, but I would prefer to
invest the tempo that we have into a
developing move. And there's only one
logical developing move. The reason we
played e6 is in order to pave the way
for knight g to e7. And I think that
that's what we should do. Let's go
knight g e7.
Obviously, our opponent's still in
theory. So, I don't like facing prep
that's this extensive. Bishop b3, okay.
I understand why he did this, though.
The point of bishop b3 is to take the
sting out of the move d5, which we were
sort of threatening. Now, d5 can be met
with e5. Of course, the bishop is no
longer hanging.
And I don't want to play d5 e5 because
that creates big dark square holes
both in the center and on the king side.
I don't love d5. It's a move that we
would play if we were desperate.
I think that we can essentially continue
developing.
So, I don't see a compelling reason that
we shouldn't castle king side.
I mean, again, we could play a6, but I
don't really see the reason to do that.
Yeah, I think we should just castle.
And let's see how white responds.
And this is very extensive preparation
by our opponent. So, big big kudos.
Okay. So, now we have a position that I
know a little bit better because this is
essentially an open Sicilian type
structure. You can compare this to an
accelerated dragon. The biggest
difference is that here our knight is on
e7. Here we have a pawn on e6, and both
of those things don't occur that often
in the accelerated. But, by and large,
in terms of the structure in the center
and the fact that d4 has been played, we
have
a more similar type of position to the
open Sicilian. Now, how are we going to
proceed?
Okay. Well, first of all, we have the
option to trade knights, which could be
good, could be bad. It's hard to say.
So, we could trade and then bring the
other knight out to c6, very typical
idea in a lot of different Sicilian
structures. That's one option.
Another option is to basically play it
more slowly, but I'm worried that white
will play F5. I'm really worried about
this move F5, which could really cause
problems on our king side.
So, there is queen B6. There is queen
B6, but then white plays bishop E3 and
our queen really looks dumb on B6.
Another move that we could turn to is
knight to A5. Maybe it's a good time to
play knight A5 and get rid of this
bishop in order to take the sting out of
the move F5, which otherwise could be
really, really, really scary.
So, I actually kind of like the look of
knight A5. Yeah, let's try knight A5.
And hopefully this will finally take our
opponent out of theory.
What I like about knight A5 is it
doesn't It's not a very committal move.
So, we can chill on A5 as long as we
need to. And then at the right moment,
we could take the bishop on B3.
Obviously, like bishop A4 is a super
awkward move and that bishop could be
targeted with A6 B5. So, I'm not worried
that white's going to keep the bishop.
I'm not really worried about knight B5.
That would be a really bad move because
of queen B6 check. It would send the
knight back to D4 where we could pick it
off with the move E5.
So, I'm anticipating a developing move
like bishop E3. And then we can breathe
a little bit easier cuz I know I won't
get checkmated.
No, Alan Philip, queen B6 and E5 would
not have worked because there was this
move knight D4 to F5. Classic trick.
I'll show that after the game.
I'll write it down, actually.
Okay, so
what is going to be our kind of system
of development? Well, when I look at
this position, the bishop on C8 really
needs to be deployed. And I think the
best spot to deploy it is to B7, right?
I mean, we we could go bishop to D7, but
then our pawn on D6 gets even weaker.
And I feel like if we could bring our
bishop to B7,
at least we're exerting some pressure on
white's center. So, here I would not
rush with knight takes B3 because we
could play this move
whenever we want to. And of course,
knight takes B3 creates a positional
concession. It opens up the A file, so
white will be able to develop some
pressure on our queen side.
So, I think that we should go on with B6
and prepare to complete our development.
C4, okay.
So, C4, our opponent starts playing this
very positionally.
But, he's really extending himself
pretty far in the center and on the
queen side. This pawn could end up as a
weakness. So, we could play bishop B7
here. That would be the standard move.
Another move that's on my radar is
bishop to A6.
I mean, if he put a pawn on C4, we might
as well try to attack it with bishop A6.
And we also put the knight on A5, so it
would really justify the placement of
our pieces.
Bishop B7 I like because he can't play
bishop C2 to defend the pawn. C4 will
hang. So, bishop B7, probably he's going
to bring the queen up to D3.
And then we could for example play rook
C8. You know, we could play this more
normally.
But, bishop A6 looks spicy. I really
want to
grab whoa. Okay. Now, our opponent has
started to just pre-move. I If this is
still preparation, I would be absolutely
shocked.
Okay, let me think about this. This is a
dangerous move. I I forgot that F5 is a
thing now that we moved our bishop away
from C8.
So, what do we do here? We could grab
the pawn on C4.
We could definitely grab this pawn.
That would attack the bishop, so white
would have to respond to that. And if
white would take our knight, then we
would take white's bishop.
We would be attacking the rook on F1.
And once the rook moved, we could play
something like E5 in order to close down
the center and go after white's F5 pawn.
So, I don't see a compelling reason that
we can't take on C4. F takes E6 would
block would blunder the bishop on E3
with a fork. That doesn't seem
dangerous.
I'm going to call white's bluff. I I
Oh, maybe Bishop G5 actually. Wait a
second. Bishop G5 might be annoying.
Because that threatens pawn F6. Wait,
wait, wait. Bishop G5 is a is a problem
there. So, let's think about this. Takes
Bishop G5.
We could play H6 there, but then there's
knight C6. No, no, this is this is bad.
Uh so, maybe we should play the
immediate E5.
Maybe we should play the immediate E5.
But then there's still Bishop G5.
Amazing. Okay, Bishop takes D4 same
problem.
I just have to think about this for a
little while.
Okay. Let's go E5. Let's go E5
and try to kick the knight out of D4. If
the knight moves back, then I'll be
really happy because then we can just
take on F5. And of course, our king side
is compromised, but it's not that easy
for white to checkmate us here. With a
bishop sitting on G7
and our pieces clustered around the
center, I think we'll be fine. Knight
B5.
Okay, G takes F5 maybe.
I don't want to take this knight and
open up the diagonal for white's bishop.
We can do that whenever we want to.
So, G takes F5 knight takes D6 is
chaotic.
But chaotic is good. We want chaotic
here.
Okay, let's play GF. Let's play GF for
now.
Because otherwise, you know, that pawn
on F5 is a huge problem for us. And
we're down to 6 minutes. Our opponent
with over 15 minutes left. This is
incredible. Very, very deep knowledge of
this opening by white.
Yeah, I don't know exactly what we're
going to do if he takes on D6. This is
just a very hard position to wrap our
head heads around and
don't feel like it's easy for me to wrap
my head around it. It's just chaotic.
So, basically in such positions, the
first person to blunder loses. We're
just going to try to avoid blundering
and play logical moves.
Yeah, finally our opponent is out of
prep, which is good. I mean, we're
almost mated here, but that's okay.
We'll survive.
We will survive. Cue the Gloria Gaynor
song.
Okay, so what what are we expecting
here? Well, there's there's many ways
for white to play. In the Grand Prix
attack traditionally, the way that
you're recommended to to meet G takes F5
is by trying to stick the queen on H5.
So, from that perspective, knight G5 may
seem terrifying. But it wasn't. I don't
think it was. Knight takes D6. All
right, so what I what I like here is the
move F4. I think that we should try to
dry up the king side as much as possible
because that's going to buy us a little
bit of time that we could use to kind of
untangle and coordinate our pieces a
little bit better. So, so to me F4 is a
bit of a no-brainer because we hit the
bishop, we create a little bit of a
defensive a defensive, you know,
bullwark on the king side that'll make
it harder for white to infiltrate. And
we buy ourselves a tempo. And white was
obviously threatening in this position
to play E takes F5. That is a pawn that
we did not want to give up because
that's a pawn which protects our king.
So, let's start with F4.
And after the bishop moves away,
after the bishop moves away,
we have to decide how to address the
problem of this knight on D6, which is
right in my grill. It's pissing me off.
This knight is pissing me off. I want to
address this knight.
Now, we have two fundamental ways that
we can try to get rid of this knight. We
could try to trade it or we could try to
hit it with our pieces. And if we want
to hit it with our pieces, the best way
I think to do that is to try to get a
rook to D8 because the queen alone is
not exerting sufficient pressure.
So, after bishop F2, which I'm
expecting, we could consider a move like
queen to C7
in order to get the rook to D8. Okay,
that's a reasonable move. It also puts
more pressure on the C4 pawn. Yeah.
The downside of playing and C7 is that
the knight could return to b5 with tempo
and hit the queen.
But then we've accomplished our aim and
the queen could tuck itself away on
let's say b7 maybe.
And then we could bring our rook to d8
anyway and start getting our pieces into
the game.
Another thing I would point out, a move
that I really would like to play at some
point is knight e7 to g6. Just as a you
know, just as a way to solidify the e5
pawn and to to you know, bring a little
bit more beef to the king side, but I
don't want to play this move when the
knight is still sitting on d6. And the
reason why is I don't want to give away
the outpost on f5 for white's knight.
That is a very nasty outpost in most
positions, this one included. So knight
g6 is I'm making a mental note to myself
to make that move a little bit later
when the smoke clears.
But right now we're going to keep our
knight on e7 to protect the f5 square
and to protect the d5 square against you
know, a move like queen to d5 and stuff
like that. By the way, if if after
bishop f2, we wanted to trade the knight
on d6, we could do that with this
retreating move knight a5 to b7.
Which is not a move that I would really
discount easily. Knight b7 is a good
positional move. We're getting rid of
our opponent's strongest piece.
In the event of the trade, our bishop
moves back to b7 and puts pressure on
e4. I like that.
After knight to b7, white could decline
the trade by dropping his knight back to
b5.
Then our knight on b7 is a little bit
awkward, but maybe we could bring it
around to c5. So that's another option
that we could explore. A lot of you are
asking about knight g5 here. I I am
skeptical about knight g5 because I
don't see what it does.
After knight g5, I feel like we could
even just play h6.
And in that position, maybe you're
scared of queen h5, but I think we could
just take the knight on g5.
The big problem for white is that he
doesn't have the services of his bishop.
If there was no pawn on e4, then the
Bishop could move back to c2 and exert
serious pressure on h7. I feel like the
queen and the knight alone just aren't
fast enough. Also, we've taken the rook
largely out of commission by building up
this pawn chain. So, knight g5 we might
face,
but I I'm not too scared of it.
And I'm scared of most things, so
I don't think this is going to work.
Yeah, of course after h6, white could
play knight takes f7. And then we would
play rook takes f7, knight takes f7. We
might even snap the queens off the
board. And then we would recapture the
knight on f7. And we would have What
would we have? We would have two pieces
for the rook. And our minor pieces are
quite well placed. Like our pieces on a5
and a6 are doing a job, right? They're
attacking c4. So, I'm fine with an end
game here. I'm I'm fine with the queens
getting off the board. Our pieces are
not poorly placed.
Well, because if white ever plays c5,
then we could take on b3. Remember that.
Right? That's why we put our knight on
a5 to to really take the sting out of a
move like c5.
He disconnected. I don't think so. I
think our opponent is just thinking.
There's a lot to think about here.
There's a lot to think about here for
white. I would play Bishop f2 pretty
quickly. 95. I saw this move.
I knew that this existed. I wasn't
taking it very seriously. Maybe I should
have.
So, let's let's try to deconstruct this
move. What What on earth is is happening
here?
What on earth is happening here?
So, two pieces are hanging. That's the
way I see it. There's the Bishop on e3
and there's the knight on e5. Either of
them can be captured. We could also take
on b3, but forget about Forget about
that for now.
My intuition, and probably yours is the
same, tells me to take on e5.
Because that's the problem piece. But
let's actually try to calculate. If we
instead take on e3,
I would imagine that white's idea is to
play knight takes F7.
Okay.
Knight takes F7. What if we just move
our queen there?
What's the big whoop? I guess the big
whoop is that white plays C5.
And opens up a line of fire toward our
king. And if we take on B3, then white
takes back with a queen and is
threatening all sorts of shenanigans.
Okay, let's think about this a little
bit more. FE knight takes F7, we could
play rook takes F7. Rook takes F7.
And in that position
might be able to throw in the move E2.
Okay, I need to think about this
carefully.
Because I I think I've understood his
idea after bishop takes E5.
Which I think is just to play bishop
takes F4. But that's not too scary.
Bishop takes E5. Another thing to
remember is that if white delivers a
check on G4, how should we deal with
that check? Well, we shouldn't bring our
king into the corner because then it
could get checkmated potentially with
knight takes F7. I think the bishop E5
queen G4, the beauty of this knight on
E7 is that it could block any check with
knight to G6.
So, I'm going to play this move largely
on the basis of intuition.
But I calculated F takes E3 just enough
to understand that the resulting
position is extremely chaotic and hard
to evaluate. Generally, you want to
avoid such positions if you have a
choice. All right, sometimes you don't
have a choice.
And it sometimes you're on the losing
side. And if you're on the losing side,
that's exactly what you want. All right,
you want to create chaos. Here, it's a
little bit easier to assess the
position. Our king is pretty safe.
Bishop takes F4, I think is the best
move. So, first of all, we can trade
queens. If we want to, we could play
queen takes D6 here, okay?
Then white would have to take, otherwise
he's two minors down. Bishop D6 bishop
D6. But obviously, that resulting
position is not over. White has two
pawns for the piece.
Our pieces are kind of discombobulated.
I think that we are winning after rook
f8. I think technically that position is
probably going to be a win. But I'd like
to find something better if at all
possible. The alternative I think is to
take on f4. The rook recaptures and we
play a move like knight to g6 to start
you know, to start getting our pieces to
better squares.
I'm apprehensive though about leaving
the queens on the board, especially
given our time situation.
So from the perspective of playing like
a Russian schoolboy, bishop queen takes
d6 makes sense.
From the perspective of trying to be as
accurate as possible,
I think probably it'll end up that
bishop takes f4 is the best move. But
again, I'm trying to give you a
realistic portrayal of what I actually
would play and what I actually would
play
in a real game
given the time situation is queen takes
d6. It's not a glamorous move.
But it's not going to win us any beauty
prizes, but what I know is that it gets
into an end game where we are up a minor
piece and white has no clear attack
against our king anymore.
And clearly I think this move was missed
by our opponent.
No, I take bishop takes b2 why, right?
Why would you need this this meaningless
pawn and give white a tempo for an
attack? I'm sure the engine would
probably claim that black is still
winning after bishop takes b2. Maybe
even we could drop our bishop back to
g7. That's a move that wasn't on my
radar at all, but probably should have
been. Bishop g7. Just simple, bring the
bishop back, keep an important defender,
and just ask white what on earth you
have.
And the answer is basically nothing.
But queen takes d6 is, you know, really
the simplifying move. White has to take
because queen g4 check here is
completely innocuous. We just go knight
g6 and the attack is over.
Bishop takes e5, we play queen takes e5,
we're two minor pieces up.
So nothing to think about here for our
opponent. I don't know what he's what
he's
going on about here.
But queen D6, bishop D6, bishop D6 is
pinning our knight. So, how should we
defend against this pin?
How should we defend against this pin?
And there is a very important tactical
detail that I calculated, which I
haven't told you guys about yet.
So, how should we how should we play
this? Well, the move is
self-evident, right? We we want to not
just defend the knight, but we also want
to solve the underlying problem of the
pin. So, rook after E8 is basically
automatic.
Now, in such situations
and we encountered a very similar
position. Yeah, that is the move that I
saw. I had to see this move when I was
calculating queen takes D6. We did
something very similar in a speed run
game couple games ago. I'll show you
after the game. Bishop A4 is scary
because it hits the rook. We can't move
the rook because we drop the knight on
E7. So, you might say, "Well, then I
have to block on C6." But if we play
knight EC6, well, you can see how
awkward that is. And maybe white has the
move B4.
But instead we have a tactic. And how do
you find this tactic? Well, what is the
drawback of the move bishop A4? Does it
actually release white's control over
anything? Yes, there's the C4 pawn and
you should see the possibility of knight
takes C4 as an interesting possibility
even though you don't it's hard to
calculate. So, knight takes C4.
If white moves the bishop from D6, then
we can intercept white's bishop with B5,
okay?
But if after knight takes C4 white takes
the rook, which bishop do you take?
And that's an easy question, right?
Comparison should tell you that the a
bishop on D6 is the one that you want to
take because in that resulting position
you're attacking the rook and you're
attacking the bishop on E8. White can't
save both at the same time. We're going
to end up in a position where we have
three minor pieces against a rook. Now,
three minor pieces against a queen is
double-sided. Three minor pieces against
a rook in most cases is an overwhelming
amount of material for the minor pieces,
even in an end game where the rooks
often benefit.
Even in an end game where the rooks
Okay, so
this is winning for black.
Bishop takes C4 I didn't like as much.
Bishop takes C4
maybe works.
Actually, maybe we can squeak by with
that move, but I didn't like it.
And I'll show you after the game.
So, knight takes C4 was a critical
detail missed by our opponent.
Bishop takes E8, knight takes D6.
And another important detail is that F7
is protected by our knight.
So, bishop takes F7 check would have
released the bishop from our clutches,
but we just take it with our knight. In
fact, I would do that with white. I
think that's the only way that he can
get, you know, a pawn for the piece.
But then we have
three minor pieces for a rook and two
pawns, which is not over, right? The
game is not over there. We would have to
demonstrate some technique, but I think
black is winning.
What if bishop B4? Well, then B5.
Toxic beans? Then B5.
Bishop B4, we play B5.
And we're chilling.
And that's of course something that you
have to see also, which is that when you
eliminate the pawn, and you should ask
yourself that question
whenever you eliminate a pawn or a
piece, you know, what was that pawn or
piece actually doing? What was it
controlling? And when you ask yourself
that question, sometimes you you
discover that, well, certain pawn breaks
or certain moves are now possible in the
absence of that pawn or piece.
Okay, so it's just something that you
always want to get into the habit of
doing, particularly if it's an important
pawn or piece. One that's in the center,
one that's controlling a lot of squares.
What new resources are possible, then
anybody should be able to see B5.
Our opponent is exhausting most of his
time. I don't know what for. I mean,
Bishop E8 is largely forced.
What's funny is that if white moves No,
actually Bishop B4 yet B5, we would have
to untangle our pieces there, but it
would not be too difficult to do that.
The power of simplification.
Yeah, so Bishop E8, knight D6, Bishop
takes F7 check, knight takes F7.
Then white's going to move the rook
probably up to F3.
And then our next project will be to
coordinate our minor pieces so that they
are actually all working together and
defending each other.
And in that resulting position, what we
would have to prevent is kind of the
rook infiltration to the seventh rank.
Because rooks are stronger than minor
pieces when they're able to gain kind of
maximum activity.
Okay, Bishop B4. I'm relieved to see
that move. I think it's easier for black
to win in this position.
So, now we play B5. That's a no-brainer.
Intercepting the Bishop. And now next
step for us is to consolidate. And
consolidating, that's a word that a lot
of people misunderstand. It basically
just means you have a situation where
your pieces are kind of scattered around
the board and they're not well
coordinated. Can we bring those pieces
onto good squares such that they're
working together
uh etc. etc. Now here, there's an
interesting moment because you might
notice that the rook is x-raying the E4
pawn. I think a lot of you are probably
thinking let's go knight C6.
After knight C6, the Bishop will drop
back to C3. And if we take the pawn on
E4, I'm a little bit apprehensive about
the move rook to F3 in that position.
And white tries to lift the rook up to
G3. And this Bishop on C3 is controlling
the retreating square on H8. If black
can send us If our opponent can send us
in the direction of F8, well, maybe
that's a little bit little bit scary in
time pressure.
So, let's see if we can find anything
safer.
I think there is a safer option, which
is not to play knight c6, but to play
knight to g6. I want a little bit I want
a bodyguard on the king side just to
make sure that there's no shenanigans
that are awaiting us on the on the g
file.
Does that make sense? Let's go knight
g6.
Rook f3. Yeah, our opponent was
basically waiting to pre-move that. I
guess we should have played knight to c6
because that would have won the bishop.
Let's think about this for a second.
If we play rook takes e4, there is the
move rook f1. That's a little bit
annoying, actually.
That is a little bit annoying.
But I think we have a winning tactic
there.
I think we have a winning tactic there.
Yeah, I think we can play rook e4.
I think we can grab this pawn.
Now, what do I see
when we play rook takes e4? Well, what I
see What is the rook on e4 doing? Well,
again, x-rays x-rays x-rays super
important.
And here you should see that the rook is
x-raying the bishop.
Now, what does that tell us? Well, that
tells us that if we move the knight,
we'll be attacking
the bishop on b4, but it is scary to
move the knight because it also opens up
the line of fire to the f7 pawn. So, we
have to move the knight on such a square
such that we take the sting out of the
move bishop takes f7 check. Of course,
we play knight e5.
Of course, we play knight e5.
There is a slightly scary option though
that I missed. There must be a way out.
Yeah, there is a way. There is a way for
us to keep our extra piece. If our
opponent does this, then I'll mention
it.
No, rook f7 I saw. Rook f7, we play
knight f7.
And basically, we're up a rook. Rook f7
Bishop f7.
King g7.
Yeah, I I allowed this to get
complicated. This was this was a very
sloppy by me.
And I think there is a way for white to
make this super complicated.
But this is going to take a little bit
of GM magic.
Yeah, no, this was
We should have just played We should
have just played rook D8. And again,
this is the lack of prophylaxis. I was
impatient. Uh this is a very instructive
mistake cuz I got impatient. I wasn't
willing to invest exactly two more
moves, and then there would be no
threats, and we could just proceed and
bring the bishop back and win the game
easily. No, I had to play rook E4, and I
missed this. Knight F7.
We have to trade. Take on F7.
And now we bring the king up to G7.
And what I saw
was that if but Yeah, crap. Our opponent
found everything here.
Okay.
King H6.
King H6, we have to go there.
And this is where I missed a move.
I calculated up to this point. I did
calculate up to this point, and the only
thing that I saw was bishop to D5. This
is what I saw.
And after bishop to D5, what we
essentially can do is say, "Okay, we're
going to lose one of our rooks, but we
can connect the rooks so that if white
takes the rook, we take the bishop, and
then we're up a minor piece, and we're
finally essentially home free."
Then we're finally I mean, it's still
It's still not that easy to convert
because our bishop is terrible,
but that I think we will be able to win.
We also have B4. Yeah, B4 is definitely
a resource to keep in mind.
But this is going to get very, very
dicey if white finds the right move
here,
which I won't mention, but
not that I'm suspecting our opponent of
anything of of stream sniping.
Obviously, 100% not.
Actually, wait a second. There's a crazy
idea.
Oh my god, it might actually work. I
need to calculate it.
Wildly difficult to calculate in time
pressure.
There is a beautiful idea that we have.
I could have played it on this move.
I could have played it on this move. So,
the move that I'm scared of, that I
didn't see, is bishop back to D2 check.
That's the move I failed to anticipate,
bishop D2 check. I only saw bishop D5.
I only saw bishop D5.
And then I think we're fine.
Still it Still it's dicey. Still it's
dicey in that position, but I think
we'll be able to win.
But the move that I missed was bishop D2
check. Why is it so scary? Because king
H5 is terrifying in that position. We
could get mated there. Rook F5 check.
Maybe it's mate, maybe it's not, but
it's scary.
So, after bishop D2 check, if we go back
to G7, white just keeps repeating moves,
bishop D2, bishop C3. And we can't go
back to F8. That's another big problem,
because then we walk right into a
discovered attack, and white wins all of
our pieces.
There is an idea. Okay.
Yeah, let me think. Okay.
Well, let's repeat moves once. That's
not going to hurt. That's not going to
hurt.
Definitely not going to hurt.
Okay. I think I might have figured out a
brilliant win.
But it hinges on
basically move-for-move calculation. So,
if I'm wrong, we're worse. Okay, I don't
know what our opponent is thinking
about, because bishop C3 is absolutely
forced.
Bishop C3 is absolutely forced.
And then my idea is to play knight E5,
which itself is not a a surprising move
for people, I think.
Knight E5.
But after bishop D5, I think we might
have a crazy resource. Let's give it a
shot. Let's give it a shot. Knight E5.
So,
knight E5 is a logical move, but it
seems to fail to bishop D5, and it
appears that we're losing the game
there, because we're losing all of our
pieces
after bishop D5. But there, I think I
found a resource that involves
identifying the x-ray against the white
rook on F1 and playing what move?
What am I What do I have my eye on here?
Yeah, B4.
Which leads to absolute chaos because
now both everything is hanging.
Everything except the bishop on D5 is
now hanging.
Oh, he found rook F7.
But wait a second. Rook F7
is not scary, I think, because we have
to go up to
Where do we go? Let me think about this.
We have to go to G6, I think. King G6 is
the critical move.
Yeah, I saw this. King G6.
And if white takes on E4, okay, wait.
There's no way this move works.
Or does it?
Oh my god, what is happening here? Wait
a second.
No, I don't think this works because I
think we can just play BC.
No, it's still complicated there.
Or can we play knight F3 check?
Can we play knight F3 check?
GF3 rook E6 Yeah, knight F3 wins.
Knight F3 just wins the game.
And I did I almost didn't see this move.
It comes out of nowhere. You wouldn't
think that there's like a discovery
against white's king that ends the game,
but there is.
Well, the positive news is that we will
have some very exciting analysis to do.
This is going to be really fun.
Yeah, knight F3 check wins because pawn
takes F3, everybody should
be able to calculate the resulting line.
We play rook takes E7. White takes the
rook on A8. We take the bishop on C3,
and we are up a full rook in that
resulting position, okay? Not a hard
line to calculate.
The moment And how did I see it? Well,
because I looked at the position with
kind of a fresh pair of eyes. I'll tell
you what I was fixated on before. The
moment I took a step back and like
asked myself, can I make any other
observations like do can I see anything
else interesting about this position?
That's the moment I spotted that there
is a connection a standoff between the
rooks.
This is the importance of taking the
broader perspective. I can see according
to the engine that BC is also winning,
but it's a lot less convincing.
Okay, so I propose that we start let's
start from the start and let's be
patient. I want to look at the opening
first and then we will get to the end
game pretty quickly. I won't take too
long on the opening, but this is an
opening related speed run. So I want to
do at least a little bit of theoretical
analysis every game.
All right, so I'm going to pull up chess
base.
And Grand Prix is giving me some
problems.
The Grand Prix attack I think is one of
the best anti-sicilians along with the
Alapin
and I I think a lot of title players and
a lot of good players just don't really
study it that that seriously even though
it's you know, it is a very serious
opening.
It is a very serious opening. So E4 C5
knight C3 you play G6.
Now
we have played this move once before.
And I distinctly remember in that speed
run
we talked about a move that tries to
essentially exploit
the drawback of the move G6. What is a
move that white has which tries to
specifically
capitalize on the fact that black hasn't
got a knight C6.
And this may seem like a very scary
move, but it we analyzed it and it's not
bad for black. Yeah, so D4 right and
after CD Queen D4
if I mean clearly you're punished for
the knight not being on C6 and we
analyzed this line knight F6
and if white plays E5 this is very
important to remember black plays knight
C6 with Tempo. This is the critical
resource and black is okay here. I
remember us analyzing this position.
So, instead of E5, white is best advised
to play,
you know, knight F3 or something like
that.
But,
black is doing fine here. This is
essentially a dragon-like position. This
is a dragon-like position where white is
slightly better according to the engine.
I think Duda-Carlsen had this. I won't
analyze this again. You can find this in
the previous video where we had this
line.
In the game, white plays the Grand Prix
attack, F4. So, bishop G7, knight F3,
knight C6. Here, white is at a further
crossroads as far as I remember.
Uh there is bishop B5, which we've
already faced. In this game, we face the
old-school move, which is still very,
very dangerous, bishop C4.
So, let's see what the top guys actually
do here. Let's see what the best way for
black to handle this actually is because
I don't think it's the way that I
played.
Okay, so according to the engine, E6 and
D6 are both legitimate moves.
So, we can go with D6 for now.
And if we don't like what we see, we can
take a look at E6. So, D6, castles, E6.
Computer gives equality, tiny edge for
black, which it always does in the Grand
Prix attack. And white plays this very
risky, but very dangerous move, D4.
So, here we responded correctly. The
move is C takes D4.
White plays knight to B5.
Black plays knight G to E7.
And according to the engine, at least at
a lower depth,
the computer actually does like the move
A6, but it also likes knight G7. It
gives equality here.
Bishop to B3 is correct.
So, this is theory.
And castles is correct.
Knight B takes D4. Knight A5 is the top
move. Okay, so I can improvise on my
feet. This is the top engine line with
knight A5.
And it along with a couple of other
lines which the computer assigns as
equal 0.00. There are still games in the
database. There are still games in the
database. 23 games, including some
grandmaster games after Bishop E3.
Now we played B6. Still games in the
database.
But B6 it likes a little bit less. It
still gives it as equal.
Okay, so I think B6 is normal.
And C4 is not a novelty.
It was played in 2022
by a grandmaster, Lars Oskar Hauge,
against another grandmaster in a
tournament in Iceland. It was played by
two Icelandic grandmasters.
So clearly this is still preparation.
And Bishop A6 was played in that game.
Oh my god. Bishop A6 was played. And our
opponent played the best move. F5 is an
improvement
is an improvement over the move that was
played in the game, which is knight to
B5. This was played in the grandmaster
game.
And knight B5 is a very serious mistake.
It's a blunder.
Can anybody tell me why knight B5 is a
blunder? Our opponent, I mean, absolute
kudos. He knew everything here.
He knew this very, very deeply. Why is
knight B5 a horrible blunder?
And black responded correctly in the
game.
But lost the game actually. Black lost
the game but responded correctly. It's
already minus two. Yeah, D5 simply.
Simply D5. And this knight is in huge
trouble. I mean, the C4 pawn gets
undermined.
In the game, white played Queen E2.
And here D takes C4
was played, but that's a big mistake.
Apparently, according to the engine,
you're supposed to trade everything
and then play DE4.
Trade everything
and then win the pawn. And if white
plays knight to G5,
black has even Queen to D3 is very, very
strong. And obviously this is a
disaster.
So this is not acceptable for white. And
our opponent improving on the game and
get F5 gives white a pretty big
advantage according to the engine. So
Bishop A6 is actually the first mistake
of the game. Everything up to that point
was normal.
What black is supposed to do here is in
fact go Bishop to B7.
And the difference is that after F5
you're supposed to go
E F5
and now you justify the placement of the
Bishop by striking in the center with
D5.
This is the point of locating the Bishop
on B7. Now, we will check why the same
thing is not as applicable with the
Bishop on A6. That's called the method
of comparison. That's where you really
get to the bottom of why the engine
recommends what it does. But first,
let's have a look at this very
complicated position.
So, what moves would you play here with
white? I want to see what the chat
thinks white should do here.
What are some moves that we should look
at here
from black's perspective?
Yeah, Bishop G5 is my instinct. Bishop
G5 is my instinct because it threatens
F6. That's a nasty move.
I also think we should look at CD. I
don't like CD. I think CD is bad for
white. Yeah, it is bad for white because
you take the Bishop and opening up the
center favors the side with the better
Bishops. In this case, it's black.
And after A takes B3, knight takes D5. I
mean, obviously black is totally fine
here. Bishop G5 and simply knight F6.
And black is black is home free.
So, white doesn't want to take that
pawn. That would be very short-sighted.
Instead, Bishop to G5 is one of the top
engine moves.
And black has to find an only move here.
Queen up to D6.
Obvious move to prevent F6. You have to
prevent F6.
The funny thing is if instead you try to
take the Bishop first, white plays F6
anyway.
This is the reason you have to go Queen
D6. And white threatens to take both of
these pieces.
So, apparently you have to go Queen D6.
Knight to B5 is not scary because black
has a check on C5. Super important
detail.
The engine line is crazy. Queen to E1
attacking the knight again.
Now black has several moves, but one of
them is to take on D4.
Holy smokes.
Why would you give up the dark squared
bishop? Who can find the right follow up
here?
Like you almost never do this in the
Sicilian. The only reason you do this is
if you have something incredibly
concrete. If you have a specific tactic,
then you take on D4.
Who can spot the follow up move? No, the
follow up has to be something specific.
It can't just be rook E8, then why did
you give up your bishop?
Right? It has to be something concrete.
It is D takes C because the knight on D4
is undefended.
The knight on D4 is undefended.
Because the point is if white plays
bishop E7, then you play queen takes D4
check, and then you can take the other
bishop.
So white has to defend this knight at
all costs with rook to D1.
Now this is crazy. Now you play F6, it's
equal 0.00. Bishop F4, only move.
Queen D5, only move.
Threatening checkmate.
Rook F2, only move. Defending against
mate. Take the bishop, knight E6.
Line is still continuing and it's only
moves for both sides here.
This is engine analysis. Queen E4,
rook E2, only moves. Every other move
would lead to an advantage for either
side. Queen F5,
knight F8,
knight D5, only move.
Bishop D6,
knight C4,
queen H4, only move. It's leading to a
draw, just you wait. Takes, queen H7,
and it's a perpetual check. Check.
Check.
Check because the king can't cross the E
file.
This is the Sicilian, ladies and
gentlemen.
And and this is why people are asking,
why is it hard to make a course on the
Sicilian or a course in general?
I mean, this is the reason.
Because of lines like this.
This is a ridiculous engine line and it
all starts it's normal until Bishop
takes D4. This is what causes the
pandemonium.
Now, black has alternatives here to
Bishop takes D4. There is the more
conventional move rook A8, although the
position is no less crazy.
Because here the line goes knight B5.
Queen C5 check Bishop B3. Now, another
ridiculous engine move knight takes up
five
giving up the queen
capturing the queen
but giving up an exchange. Apparently,
black has full compensation for the
exchange here because your Bishop is a
beast and because you have a pawn.
CD5
you take the Bishop and then you take
the pawn and this is equal.
Because the Bishops are really
crisscrossing the board and offer black
sufficient compensation. So,
in a game I would play Bishop D4 cuz
that's too sexy of a move not to play.
So, that is the simple reason why Bishop
B7 is the best move in the position.
Yeah, I mean, who
I don't even really think I had to show
this. This is this is
basic betting right here.
But it's amazing to me that our
opponent's knowledge of this opening
extended past theory. Like C4 one game
in the database, recent game. So, this
was clearly white's preparation and he
improved on the play of a GM. So, now
let's understand what the difference is
after Bishop A6 F5. And the question
that you want to ask yourself is this,
what happens if black plays in exactly
the same way that you would after Bishop
B7. That's how you get to the bottom of
why a certain move is better than
another one. So, the question is after
EFEF, why can't we play the move D5?
Like, what's the actual reason?
So, apparently, according to the engine,
the reason
consists in the move knight to G5. This
is the reputation.
Now, you might say, "Well, wait a
second. Well, why wasn't knight g5 a
thing after bishop b7? Does that process
make sense? So, let's look at knight g5
here and then we'll look at it with the
bishop on a6. And eventually, we're
going to understand what the critical
difference is. If you play knight g5
here, black plays dc.
So, now we go back to the other line.
Now, we go back to the other line and we
we we check dc here.
Um we check dc here.
So, if dc here,
then black white plays fg.
And if black plays hg,
then queen g4 leads to checkmate.
Now, we go back to the other line. Why
is fg not good there?
Knight g5 dc fg.
I I hope what I'm doing actually like
makes sense.
We're just comparing the placement of
And this is the point where black has an
additional resource. See, it's pretty
easy if you know the process to follow.
Now, who can tell me? Let's see if
anybody can use logic to figure this
out. What could possibly be the virtue
of having the bishop on b7? What could
possibly be an additional resource that
solves black's problems here?
Yeah, it's queen d5.
It's queen d5 because the only thing you
can do with that bishop is threaten
checkmate. And apparently, this move
allows black to throw a spanner in the
works. White is unable to attack
properly because of the mate threat. If
white goes here,
then you go h5 dis- deflecting the
queen.
If gf, you can of course take with the
rook because the queen is hanging.
And if the queen moves back, then you
can just play bishop takes d4.
gf7, you still play rook f7.
Holy freaking smokes.
And after rook f7, you again use the
fact that the queen is tied down to g2
and you take all of white's pieces. You
just take everything and you're going to
take a fourth minor piece on the next
move, which is also hanging.
And so, that is the critical difference.
With the bishop on a6,
with the bishop on A6
um you don't have this resource of Queen
D5 here.
So, what you ultimately have to do
is play either HG and lose after Queen
to G4 because this is unstoppable.
Or if you take the bishop on B3
then you lose the game after
Queen H5. Yeah, why this is just
overwhelming attack here.
H6 is forced. GF here Oh, oh there's a
sexy move here again. Rook F6
threatening rook takes H6 with checkmate
in two moves.
Black has to go knight G8.
And now
just rook G6. This is just absolutely
crushing.
FG is coming and there's too many mate
threats here.
And that's it. Knight G5 is the big
reason that you want to play the move
bishop to B7 and that's the takeaway
from the opening in this game.
Hope you enjoyed that little excursion
into the depths of Sicilian nonsense.
Now, by the way, I should point out for
the sake of completeness that after the
move B6
after the move B6 white's main move,
like the most popular move
has been Queen to E1
because you're trying to get the queen
around to H4, but this is bad because of
Bishop A6. This is a bad move.
And the problem, this was a game between
a 2400 and a 2586 classical game.
White has to play rook F2 and then the
it begs the question, well then why did
you put the queen on E1 if you can't
even get it to H4?
And black is better after knight B3, AB3
and Bishop B7.
And black is white is experiencing
serious problems with the E4 pawn.
This is the game Wang against Zhao
Washington 2022.
In that game white played F5
and black responded cold-bloodedly with
e5.
White played Bishop g5,
which is an idea that we actually had in
the game. Interesting.
And here black responds with h6.
This is actually how the game continued.
f6,
hg, fg, King g7.
And here white found a sick tactic, but
it doesn't work. Knight g5.
e takes d4,
Rook takes f7 check.
And who can tell me how should black
respond to this move?
What should black do?
Let's see if you understand the concept
of queen disease properly.
This is such a common type of mistake
that people make.
So, a lot of people's automatic reaction
would be, "Well, I can't take the rook
because I lose my queen."
But, you have to always put it in
context. How would How would How much
are you getting for the queen?
Everybody forgets to ask this question.
You actually do want to take the rook.
And after 96 King g8 98 Rook d8, black
gets a crap ton of material for the
queen. You get two minor pieces and a
rook. Yeah, white gets another pawn on
a7, true, but we can chew the rook away
with knight c6. And white also has this
major weakness on e4, which you can
really zero in on with Rook e8. Black is
much better  winning. This is how
the game continued, actually.
So, black was able to win the game in
this way.
So, c4 is an improvement over Queen e1.
And over a couple of other moves that
was played in this position. I also see
that Queen d3 was played, but this
doesn't seem all that scary.
So, let's get to the game. f5, we
decided to play e5. The question is,
where did our opponent actually end up
going wrong? Our opponent ended up going
wrong in this position. Knight b5 is an
automatic move.
And after knight b5, already black is
doing all right. It's equal,
but with the best move, white is plus
over minus, and I saw the best move. I
missed it initially, I saw it
ultimately.
What is the best move for white? Same
idea that we just saw.
Same idea that we just saw.
You have to understand how vulnerable
these two minor pieces are.
And you have to set up the move F6. How
do you do that?
Bishop G5. Bishop G5 is best.
Now, a couple of very important details.
If black plays F6,
then white has 96, so that fails.
If black takes the knight, then F6 is
devastating.
And you might say, "Well, I don't get
why F6 is so devastating. Like, we just
won a piece. White's winning a piece
back, what's the big deal?" The problem
isn't that white is winning the piece
back, it's which piece he's winning. The
problem is we cannot keep this bishop,
and you should understand intuitively
why without this bishop
there are some exceptions. We saw an
exception, but in most cases, you cannot
survive without this bishop. If you play
bishop F6, I mean, look at this
position. Queen D2 Queen H6 is literally
unstoppable, literally.
So, that's lost, and you can't keep the
bishop because white plays FE and wins
the rook. So, that's the actual reason
this move is so scary.
Now, black should respond here with H6
and force the bishop away.
And here
white plays bishop H4 G5, and let's see
if people can once again find a move
that's very much in the spirit of the
Grand Prix attack. This leads to a crazy
line that I think you guys will really
enjoy. But, what's the move here?
Because two pieces are hanging.
So, you might think it's knight takes G5
because that's what you're used to. But,
think for a second about what piece you
want to leave on the board. Yeah, the
move is bishop G5.
Compare, right? When you compare this
position to this position, which
attacker is stronger? If you ask
yourself that question, well, clearly
this knight is the stronger attacker
because it combines with the queen.
And here black has to find an only move,
which is ridiculous, impossible move. If
black takes, then this is obviously
checkmate.
This is obviously checkmate.
Um
Rook E8, you take this pawn, you go
back, this is easy. Check, and then at
the end you have mate with 96. This is
pretty elementary patterns. Black has to
find knight E5.
And the logic of this move is
straightforward. You're trying to
eliminate the knight on G5. But why are
you putting the knight on D5? Well,
there's a secondary reason, which is
that if white plays Queen H5, then the
knight is able to drop back to F6 and
protect H7. That's why you don't go
knight C6 or knight C8 or any other
knight move.
So after knight E5,
white finds a counter blow, knight DE6.
Jesus.
F takes E6, knight takes E6, and white
just gets a huge attack.
Queen F6.
And now apparently after
Queen takes D5, it's plus over equals
it's like .6. Finally, the smoke clears.
Black plays Bishop E7 to force the queen
away.
Queen to D3, and white has overwhelming
compensation for the piece. There's the
idea of rook F3, rook G3. The knight is
a monster, and at this point white
already has three pawns for the piece.
Just mind-blowing complications with
Bishop G5. But this would have caught
put us in very serious trouble.
This would have put us in very serious
trouble.
Yeah, this is why chess is chess is so
fun. I hope I'm not going too deep.
But this is how you learn about tactics,
right? It's not just solving puzzles.
Analyzing helps you really just get to
the bottom of some of these ideas, and
it's also fun. It's fun to analyze with
an engine. It's also fun when you have a
grandmaster like guiding you around,
which is what I'm trying to do. So after
E5 knight B5,
now we're able to take this pawn, and
now black is fine.
Now black is fine.
So our opponent correctly plays knight
takes d6.
Finally, the smoke clears and here
knight e5 is a horrible move. Our
opponent is trying to play in the spirit
of the Grand Prix attack, but he just
doesn't have enough going on the king
side to justify this pawn this knight
sac.
This this knight sac is just terrible.
The correct move is bishop f2.
And according to the engine, the move
that I intended to play was best queen
c7
in order to be able to play rook a d8.
And here we were calculating knight g5.
I was mentioning this during the game.
Black has to play h6.
Why does black have to play h6? Because
if you procrastinate, then this is
devastating because the mate is
threatened and now knight f7 is
horrendous. So,
here you have to immediately root out
the knight. Knight takes f7, rook f7.
Knight f7, king f7. What should white
play here?
Who can tell me how should white proceed
continue the initiative? Otherwise,
white is much worse. This is like This
is a no-brainer. This move should be
automatic to you.
Yeah, c5. Very nice. c5.
Black takes the bishop, but the queen
replaces the bishop.
And the benefit of the queen on b3,
once the king escapes, is that white can
play cb, ab, and maybe white could grab
that pawn or white could just move the
rook away. And the engine gives equality
here, which I agree with. I think it's
just a super complicated position that's
hard to evaluate and usually that means
equal. So, this is how the game should
have continued,
but our opponent just is unable to
maintain the tension. He plays knight
takes c5. And now let's get directly to
the final stage of the game because
after bishop e5 and queen takes d6,
black is winning. Black is winning. This
is up a piece. And I just wanted to
point out before we get to the final
stage of the game
where you saw this before. So, where you
saw this before
and I just realized we played this guy
once before.
This is the second time we played this
guy. Oh, it was the Jabava London game
where I missed 94. So, no wonder we got
into a bad position. Here I was in
trouble as well.
So, this guy uh this guy knows what he's
doing.
I'm just looking for the game.
Yeah, this is the game where you saw a
very similar tactic. Remember that when
a piece is defended by another piece,
particularly if it's a rook or a queen,
you can generally chase away the
defender. So, remember this game where
we first played knight g7
and then we did the same thing with the
bishop. This is exactly what our
opponent did. Attack the attack the rook
or that's exactly what we did. And if
the rook has to move, then you take the
knight.
Now, compared to this game,
we had an additional resource in this
position,
which is of course knight takes e4.
And if bishop e8, then we play knight d6
and the rook is hanging, the bishop is
hanging. I explained this during the
game. Black is winning. So, let's go to
the game. Bishop b4, b5, bishop b3,
knight g6, rook f3, and rook takes e4
is probably not a mistake in itself, but
I think the safer move the safer move
would have been just to bring another
rook into the game. Just defend the f7
pawn and white is out of ideas. White is
simply out of ideas. Our next move is
going to be either rook takes e4 or
bishop b7. We're going to win the e4
pawn. We're going to win the game. So,
remember the power of prophylaxis. When
you stop your opponent's threats, it's
so much easier to play. I could not
resist
because I thought that I had calculated
this accurately and it turns out that
this is a lot more complicated than I
than I made it out to be.
So, what happens if white plays bishop
f7? Well, this is easy. This is easy.
You take the bishop and then you take
the other bishop and you're up to minor
pieces. But of course our opponent finds
something fancier than that. Rook takes
f7.
And this move is a lot scarier because
if you ignore the rook, then you lose
the game to rook takes a7 check. And
white will take this rook with check and
then when the bishop as well.
So, our hand is forced here. We have to
play knight f7, rook f7, bishop f7.
King g7.
And now the second important moment,
okay?
Now, in this position, white actually
had another very interesting resource,
which was the move rook takes f7. And in
order to preserve an advantage, black
has to find an only move in this
position. This is a very difficult move.
So, if you're watching on YouTube,
I highly recommend that you pause the
video and try to figure out the defense
here. Because it's very easy to blunder
here.
There is a mpwa, most popular wrong
answer.
So, the most popular wrong answer is
rook takes bishop because you might say,
"Aha, well, what is white going to do?"
Well, probably white is going to try to
win the most number of pieces, right?
So, white's going to take on a7, but I
saw one step ahead. I'm going to take
the bishop and I'm going to win. No,
you're not. White takes the rook with
check and then takes the other rook.
And if you don't take the bishop and you
move the king, you have to stay on the
eighth rank. And the problem is that you
also lose the bishop on a6 in the end.
Does that make sense?
So, if you instead move the king to the
side, this also is not going to cut it
because white's going to give you this
nasty little check on c3.
And yeah, you can block with knight e5,
but just look at this position. This is
a disaster. Everything is being lost
right now.
Or or white could play rook e7 and pick
up the knight. You're going to you're
going to lose the game here.
So, the correct idea is rook to c4,
cutting off, slicing off the discovered
attack. This is the benefit of being up
a rook. You get to give away some of
your material and here black is winning.
Black is up a piece. Now, according to
the engine, white preserves some
practical chances with rook c7 because
black's king is so bad and black's minor
pieces are so bad that it's really
really hard to untangle. And here the
best move is just to bring the bishop
around to the center. Bishop c8 is a
really strong move. And okay, black will
have to demonstrate some technique, but
this is winning. This is winning.
Does that make sense?
Um
so instead our opponent plays bishop f7,
we have to go up bishop c3, king h6 and
bishop d2 is the move that I missed. And
according to the
According to the end I I had no idea
whether we were winning or losing after
king h5. Apparently black is still
better. But can you really blame me for
not wanting to go for this position? I
mean, this is crazy.
This is crazy. Let me run Stockfish here
at a high depth and give you the best
line.
Stockfish at a high depth. This is where
the chess.com engine really is
insufficient. But positions that are
this complicated need to be looked at
with a serious engine.
So apparently
Here's the evaluation. Just a second.
The evaluation is an advantage. No, it's
equal.
Oh my god, but this is insane. This is
impossible. Apparently the best move
here is not to give this check, but
instead to play bishop d5.
So just to make sure we're on the same
page, how should black respond to this
move? How should black respond to bishop
d5?
Just to make sure everybody understand
what's going on here. Yeah, rook a8,
right? Rook a8. Now there is an only
move. If anybody finds this move in a
game, you immediately call the TD or you
you call Danny Rensch. Literally.
Literally. Apparently the best move.
There is a move that keeps equality,
which is just to take and go rook f7 and
win all of black's pawns. But the
absolute best move is h 3.
h3
and the idea is to take away the g4
square from black's king. That's the
idea. So if black moves the rook, then
there's checkmate in three moves. Check.
Check. Mate.
That's the idea. Black's king is caught
in something like a mating net here.
And black can draw with king H4.
And now white plays bishop E4, rook E4,
rook F5.
Black's king is still in serious
trouble.
But there is a perpetual check. King G3.
Check. King H4 and we have a repetition
of moves. Black can't do anything else
here. Because if instead you play a move
like bishop C8,
you get checkmated. Check.
And this is the secondary idea of H3.
Now white has G4 and you have to give up
your rook. And if you go the other way
you get checkmated.
So, yeah. So, it was a good call for me
not to go king H5. And long story short.
So, I decided to apply the final idea
knight E5. And without this idea, this
game would have been a draw. Because
without this move, and I played
correctly,
apparently this is still equal, but
white has to be super precise.
So, let me tell you what I calculated
with this move knight E5.
Oh my gosh. I calculated the
Oh my Okay, this is this is a
Okay, this is amazing. This is amazing.
You're going to enjoy this tremendously.
This is beautiful.
Okay.
Get ready. Get ready. Get ready. So,
okay. First of all, let's make sure
we're on the same page.
What is the point of knight E5? Well,
the point is that the king has nowhere
to go. Because if you go back to F8, you
get
you get massacred with bishop D5 or or
bishop G6 even better.
We've already discussed why king H6 and
king H5 doesn't work. So, I figured the
only other idea is to block with the
knight. If you try blocking with the
rook instead, this is a very ingenious
idea. The problem is that white's going
to take the knight first and then take
the rook.
Okay? So, here white plays bishop D5 and
everything hinges on this move B4 which
thrusts the game into complete and total
chaos. And here
I had to calculate a certain line that
at first sight may seem to be only
beneficial to white. What are the
possibilities here for white? Our
opponent lost the game quickly with rook
f7, that was a mistake.
What should white do instead?
Which pieces should white take?
Well, basically white has three
candidate moves, okay?
What are white's three candidate moves?
There's bishop takes knight, there's
bishop takes rook, and there's bishop
takes other rook.
Bishop takes knight is really dumb
because you just take.
And at the end white is down an
exchange, okay? So, that's ruled out.
Which rook should white take?
Well, white should actually take this
rook
because if you take the other rook,
black's going to take the bishop.
Why is black going to take the bishop?
Black is not going to take the rook here
because that allows bishop takes e5
check. So, we're going to take the
bishop, white's going to take the rook,
we're going to take the rook, and at the
end the bishop on a8 is terribly placed.
King takes f1 loses the game to c2.
Compare that to the other capture.
Bishop takes a8, same thing happens. bc,
bishop b4, bishop f1, king f1. Here the
bishop is optimally placed because c2 is
impossible. But, I saw this AND I
THOUGHT THAT black is winning here with
c takes b2.
Now, how do we assess this position?
Well, what does black want? Black wants
to get the knight over to a3 and promote
the pawn and win a piece. And it turns
out that white's king is not fast enough
because white plays king e2, that's not
the beautiful part. This all all of this
I saw. All of this I saw.
And look at this position, king d1
knight a3.
And you're preventing the king from
stopping the pawn. On the next move
black promotes to a queen and some
technique is required, but black is in
fact winning here.
Does that line make sense to everybody?
This line.
But, here's the beautiful part. After
king e2 knight C4, white has an only
drawing move. Incredible idea. I've
never seen quite this idea before.
White to play and draw the game. Again,
if you're watching on YouTube, I really
think you should set this up and take
some time on this because this is a
high-level exercise.
So, stronger players watching, you
really would want to take some time on
it.
Yeah, one of one of you got it. Well,
bishop B1 doesn't help, right? Bishop B1
doesn't do anything. It just makes it
worse because now I make this move a
tempo.
If you play bishop C2 and king D3, I'm
not going to take your bishop. I'm just
going to promote.
But hopefully you're you're spotting a
pattern, which is your basic
How do you solve this? Well, the basic
premise, the basic idea is that
in the situation after black takes on
B1, the knight is essentially trapped.
And if you keep calculating here, you
might find that king C2 almost traps the
knight. Here, the knight is able to
escape, but only through B5. That's the
only square that the knight is able to
escape through. Otherwise, you would
have to repeat moves forever, knight B1,
king C2, etc.
So, it's a prophylactic move that sets
up the drawing mechanism.
A4 is correct.
A4. Knight A3. Now, you walk the king
over.
Black promotes.
You trade, and with B5 under your
control, you're able to force a
repetition of moves.
King B3.
And knight doesn't have B5. Knight has
to go back to B1. Now, not king B2
because then the knight escapes, king
C2.
To keep the knight confined. And this is
a draw.
And that's uh
And that's how I could have drawn the
game.
Unbelievable. So, the line is in this
position
bishop A8
BC bishop E4. This is the easy part.
King E2 or A4, by the way, A4 even here
is good. Doesn't matter what the order
is. But you can't forget to play A4
because otherwise the knight sits on A3
and your pawn is immobilized.
This is brilliant. A4.
Drawing move.
This absolutely should be used. I'll use
this in some video because I'll
eventually do a book or a Chessable
course like best moments from speed run
series, most instructive moments, and
this is one of them. This is
unbelievable.
I'd be one king C2. I hope you found
this as beautiful as I did.
So, bishop A8 could have drawn the game,
but instead our opponent gives this
tempting check, and now the problem is
that if white tries to do the same
thing, right? If white plays bishop
takes A8 now, well, it's not going to
work anymore because at the end of this
line, what's the difference? Well, the
difference is the bishop used to be on
F1.
Here black is not making us be the one
to take the rook with a king with a
bishop instead we're taking the rook
with a king, and white loses.
So, our opponent tried this move, but we
win the game immediately with knight F3.
Probably the most resilient would have
been to play bishop takes C4 check and
bishop takes C5. This would have kept
white in the game because here white has
a pawn for the exchange, but black is
still winning. Black is still winning.
Not a piece. We are not winning a piece
because of this check,
but black should win this with technique
because the center is wide open, and the
rook should prevail in this case.
So, this would have been the best chance
for
for black, but uh for white, but still
um
Okay, we can't blame our opponent for
collapsing with the rookie 7. I almost
missed knight F3 check. It's an easy
move to forget about.
And that, ladies and gentlemen, is this
one of the most complicated games that
we have played. I had a feeling that we
were going to get something good, and we
did.
So, in conclusion, G6 is a good move
against knight C3 if you're an
accelerated player.
Then, everything here was correct. We
followed theory. Now, if you're a theory
junkie, you can investigate E6 on your
own. I'm not going to do that in this
video just because I want to keep things
at a normal length. The way we played
was fine.
Our opponent played this very dangerous
modern line with D4. We responded to it
correctly by developing our pieces.
Bishop B3 by the way is a nice move.
Um and the idea is to take the sting out
of the move D5.
Prophylaxis. We responded correctly with
knight A5 and B6. And this is still
theory.
This was our mistake, bishop A6. So the
improvement is bishop B7.
Then the improvement for our opponent
would have been to play bishop G5.
And then of course the situation
remained very complicated. He gave up a
piece. Here bishop F2 would have kept an
unclear position.
And then
fast forward all the way to the end
the beautiful draw with
bishop takes A8 after B4.
Any questions?
Okay.
You have said G6 and E6 is wrong. Why
not now? So great question.
Um in previous speed runs I have claimed
that in the Sicilian you normally don't
want to combine the moves G6 and E6.
That is true. I have claimed that. But
there is a major caveat, which is that
Okay, positionally it's quite dubious to
combine G6 and E6, but normally it all
relates to whether or not your opponent
can gain control of the D6 square.
Okay, in this position the D6 square is
under black's control.
All right? The D6 square is under
black's control. But I could also show
you a situation
where black plays G6 and E6 and white is
able to stick
a queen on D6 or a knight on D6 or black
white is able to play E4 E5 and really
clamp down on that square. That's when
you want to be very careful about
combining these two moves. Here's an
example
of a game of mine. I've shown this game
many times, but I think it's the best
illustration of when not to play E6 and
G6.
And this will hopefully give you a
little context on like the difference
between
you know, this game and
this game in and situation where it's
bad to combine these two moves.
Old game of mine. I would I managed to
win this game, but look at what happens.
So, my opponent plays the Smith-Morra. I
made the mistake of taking.
At that point, I had no idea what the
theory was. So, I decided to play G6.
And here, I decided to make a genius
move and play E6.
So, what is the chief difference between
this version and the version that we had
in our game? Well, look at the fact that
white has a direct line of fire to the
D6 square. So, he could have played
Queen D6 immediately, but instead he
starts with knight B5.
And that's it. Already, D6 is under
white's complete control.
But instead of giving the check on D6,
which a lot of people would have done,
he plays Queen to D6, which wins the
game because knight C7 is literally
unstoppable. You can't do anything about
that move. I had to play Queen E7.
And I end up losing a full rook. I win
this game because I ultimately end up
winning the knight back. And I also
grabbed the pawn in the center. So, it's
not that easy to convert, but you get
the point.
You get the point.
It's It's all about whether the center
is open.
Also, you have to be very careful
uh in a situation where white is able to
play the move E5 and clamp down on the
D6 square. Let me show you one more
example
of a very famous game. The end of this
game is very famous. The beginning not
as famous,
but still very instructive. We won't
look at the whole game.
I'll just show you the mistake that
black makes early on.
Okay, here it is.
So,
this is a Petrosian-Pacman game, which
ends with a famous queen sacrifice.
Somewhat overrated combination to end
this game,
but here is what Pacman does wrong in
the opening. Not David.
Ludek.
So, basically, here Pacman plays d6 and
e6, which is fine.
But then he forgets to play d6.
Here you have to play d6. He forgets to
do it. And what does Petrosian do?
What does Petrosian do?
How does he punish Pacman for not
playing d6?
He basically clamps down on the dark
squares. Yeah, he plays e5.
And it's not such a big issue. Black
plays d6, but this resulting position is
terrible because now black is like
this, you know, black's structure is
worse and white's knight is coming to e4
and this pawn is weak and the bishop is
bad. So it would have been much, much
better just to avoid all of this by
playing d6.
Those are a couple of examples of when,
you know, black paid the price for
playing these two moves. Yeah, this was
a this was a bad game for black.
And that's that. We're going to conclude
here. Thank you for watching if you were
on YouTube.